Arafat Hassan

hassanarafat@yahoo.com

linkedin.com/in/arafat-hassan1

https://arafathassan1.github.io

Summary

Earned a Bachelor of Science (BS) focused in Geographic Information Science and a minor focusing in City and Regional Planning from The Ohio State University. Skilled in administering/managing databases and using GIS/ visualization related softwares such as ESRI ArcGIS tools, ERDAS Imagine, QGIS, Tableau, etc. Continuously learning programming languages such as JAVA, HTML, Arcade Expressions, Python, R Programming, etc. Extensively experienced in Microsoft Office (Excel, Word, Powerpoint, etc.), Google Drive, ETL process, retail, and customer service.

Experience



GIS Database Administrator

Ohio Department of Natural Resources

Mar 2023 - Present (1 year 1 month)

- Manage, identify, and implement in SSMS/ArcSDE (Enterprise Geodatabase) any improvements that can be implemented in department-wide ArcSDE for optimal performance for GIS users by rebuilding indexes, clearing archived records, updating statistics, compressing via scripts, etc
- Manage and coordinate the maintenance of department-wide non-spatial database systems (SQL Server) using SQL Server Jobs in SQL Server Mangement Studio (SSMS)
- Plan, implement, and enhance new divisional geo-spatial database items such as vector and raster datasets
- Create new and enhances existing database elements in ArcSDE and non-spatial database with triggers, stored procedures, replication, etc
- Assist coworkers, different GIS departmental representatives, interns with any ArcSDE needs including updating schema, implementing attribute rules, automate tasks via scripts, creating views in SSMS, etc
- Document and diagram existing database environments, policies, and process for recordkeeping

Systems Analyst/GIS Administrator

City of Westerville

Feb 2022 - Mar 2023 (1 year 2 months)

- Develop short and long-range plans, goals, objectives and priorities to improve city's operational efficiency and effectiveness for GIS development and integrations
- Communicate with GIS users to determine current and future needs, and implements recommendations such as building a custom printing widget for WebGIS
- Maintain and monitor the health of the GIS servers including performing monthly updates for both ArcGIS Enterprise and ArcGIS Online
- Develop, administer, and maintain GIS web sites and applications for the internet and intranet
- Performs continuous updates of city's core GIS data and web site information
- Communicate with the general public, vendors, management, and contractors in order to coordinate GIS projects and administer the use of data such as Tyler Technologies: New World, FuturaGIS, etc.
- Represent the GIS team on committees and task forces by serving as a technical advisor in the exchange of information or in addressing specific needs

- Prepare, process, and review written documents pertaining to GIS to ensure compliance with departmental policies and procedures
- Prioritize and track time-sensitive projects and assignments to ensure timely completion
- Coordinate and oversee various special projects and/or presentations in support of the GIS system including transitioning from current aerial imagery provider, giving GIS presentation at the Citizens Academy, etc.
- Establish and maintain effective working relationships with superiors, fellow workers, and vendor's representatives
- Review programs, white-papers, research papers, attend training courses, attend GIS Steering Committee meetings, etc. to develop innovative approaches to problem solving and to make recommendations
- Develop, document, and provide GIS standards, training and guidance for GIS users within the City of Westerville

Misource GIS Technician

NiSource

Jan 2021 - Feb 2022 (1 year 2 months)

- Analyze design capital project completion information by reviewing proper pressure tests, materials, and facilities to assure compliance with proposed engineering designs, company policies, practices, standards and other applicable codes
- Update/maintain GIS and work management system to accurately reflect gas system updates using given project as-built and related documentations
- Execute capital projects including providing new gas service to new customers, public roadway improvements and relocations, gas system improvement and maintenance in a timely manner that adheres with the department metrics
- Provide technical assistance and build strong relationship through communication and collaboration with Field Engineering, Construction, M&R, and Field Operation staff
- Proactively collaborate with leaders, co-workers, and key business partners with planning group goals, objectives, and priorities to exceed department metrics
- Assist co-workers with executing their capital projects
- Guide Field Operation staff to provide accurate information for non-capital work to capital work
- Actively reaching out to participate on upcoming department projects such as beta testing migration from ArcMap to ArcGIS Pro and accurately mapping customer service lines
- Continuously learning about upcoming GIS news and tools to keep up with the industry standards and expand personal knowledge

📦 GIS Analyst/Engineering Technician I

City of Canton, Ohio

May 2019 - Jan 2021 (1 year 9 months)

- Maintain and update enterprise GIS databases with new/existing water distribution system data in a Geometric Network
- Perform quality assurance for the water distribution system data from multiple sources (field workers, historical records, engineering drawing, and AutoCAD drawings)
- Initiator of the organizational system that keeps records of the waterline projects including creating As-Builts drawings and end of the year cost reports
- Utilization of ArcGIS Pro to append data between databases
- Apply hosted feature layers in ArcGIS Pro to append next day assignments in Workforce for ArcGIS of water assets verification for interns

- Generates custom feature layers in ArcGIS Pro through digitizing to then be published as a web layer in ArcGIS Online for future presentations
- Creates web maps and applications such as dashboards by utilizing ArcGIS Online
- Utilization of Workforce for ArcGIS, Collector, and Survey123 app to perform GPS data collection
- Performs in field data collection of GPS data from new/replaced water valves, fire hydrants, curb stops, and fittings using Trimble products
- Collaborates with supervisors to plan current or next GIS project/agenda
- Provides teaching and mentorship to GIS interns
- Assists with tech support to field workers and help fix troubleshoots with the county GIS Department

GIS Planner Intern

Delaware County, Ohio

Sep 2018 - Apr 2019 (8 months)

- Assisted with converting and modifying county shapefiles from ArcView 3.2 to ArcMap 10.6 using "Import from ArcView" ArcMap extension
- Store texts/annotations including road names in a geodatabase with correct fonts and its size
- Match queries, map symbols, shapefile names, legends, title, scale bar, neatlines, north arrow in ArcMap with ArcView
- Combined converted map with updated geodatabase text annotations to export it to a PDF file
- Collaborated with supervisors to update and maintain the county maps such as new zoning, removing silvers or gaps of polygons

Retail Sales Consultant

Sprint

Dec 2017 - Apr 2019 (1 year 5 months)

- Assisted customers with their cellular needs through creating bundles that works for them.
- Exceeded key performance objectives, including sales and customer satisfaction goals

Team Member

ZAGG, Inc.

Jun 2016 - Dec 2017 (1 year 7 months)

- Collaborated with supervisors and coworkers to train new employees
- Managed store opening or closing operations, including auditing cash register and counting inventory

SEATE Barista

Columbus State Community College

Jan 2015 - Jun 2016 (1 year 6 months)

- Served customers with coffee drinks in a timely manner
- Managed store opening or closing operations

Server Assistant

Cameron Mitchell Restaurants

May 2014 - Jun 2016 (2 years 2 months)

- Assisted servers with tasks such as delivering food to serve guests better

- Organized tables in an appealing way by ensuring utensils, glasses are clean for next service

Service Champ

Taco Bell

Jun 2011 - Sep 2014 (3 years 4 months)

- Implemented a plan to serve the customers in a timelier manner at drive thru
- Trained new employees and supported existing employees with their tasks

CSL Plasma Reception Technician

CSL Plasma

Jul 2013 - Nov 2013 (5 months)

- Assisted qualified donors in completing the screening process
- Educated new donors on the use of therapeutic products made from donated plasma

Education

The Ohio State University

Geographic Information Science and Cartography, City and Regional Planning, Geographic Information Science, City and Regional Planning 2016 - 2018

Columbus State Community College

Associate of Science - AS, General Studies 2013 - 2016

Licenses & Certifications

esri ArcGIS Enterprise: Configuring a Base Deployment - Esri 50158813

esri ArcGIS Enterprise: Administration Workflows - Esri 50158893

Foundations: Data, Data, Everywhere - Coursera
PWN9VKA5VCFW

Ask Questions to Make Data-Driven Decisions - Coursera GUN73XEDMYHQ

Prepare Data for Exploration - Coursera
57VXZZPLSPUZ

Process Data from Dirty to Clean - Coursera

SWHBDTQ95J9F

- Analyze Data to Answer Questions Coursera YL7JRF3U26HZ
- Share Data Through the Art of Visualization Coursera
 A889NE8UPESY
- Futura GIS II Futura Systems
- Data Analysis with R Programming Coursera
 L5EWBZE4WLCS
- Getting Started with the FME Platform Safe Software
- FME Desktop Basic Safe Software
- Microsoft SQL Server 2016 Certification (70-764) Advance Udemy
- esri MOOC: Cartography Esri
- esri MOOC: Transform AEC Projects with GIS and BIM Esri

Skills

ArcGIS Python API • Computer-Aided Design (CAD) • Building Information Modeling (BIM) • SQL Server Management Studio • ArcSDE • Enterprise Geodatabase • MATLAB • R (Programming Language) • Tableau • Data Conversion